Guide to the George W. Wilbur Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Susan Rice's life is also documented by small files of correspondence with her sister Ellen and George Wilbur's mother Sarah Ann. Letters between Susan Rice and Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur are essentially thank you notes (folder 494). No reference to her mental illness is made in this correspondence. Letters between Ellen Rice Wilbur and Susan Rice (folder 567), were written while apart from one another. Ellen's letters in particular contain a great deal of information about her daily schedule.
George and his wife Ellen Rice (Nellie) were friends for many years before their marriage, their letters consisting of an exchange of hometown gossip and details of their daily life, with few hints of a romance between them (folders 324-326). As might be expected, the collection contains little correspondence between George and Ellen Wilbur except when one or the other traveled away from Illinois. George wrote Ellen from Colorado in 1890 and 1891 (folders 327-328), in which he describes his work at the mill he co-owned and other daily details of his life there. For the period when George returned to Colorado in 1896, the collection contains only Ellen's letters to him (folders 328-329). These letters, and those of later years, include news about their daughter Susan, and describe Ellen's daily life in Oak Park. George's later letters while on business or while Ellen traveled contain passing references to his work and domestic details. Ellen's correspondence with George's mother Sarah Ann (folders 475-476) consists of letters mostly written by Ellen, and are primarily notes settling visiting times, with news of Susan Wilbur.
George Wilbur also maintained an extensive correspondence with his brother Albert (folders 252-323). The correspondence consists principally of Albert's letters to George, with some later carbon copies of George's letters to Albert. They begin with Albert's departure from home in 1875 and are descriptive of the places to which he traveled, work, mine accidents, fires, and other news he found unusual. Albert's letters to his mother (folders 421-474) are similar in content, but his letters to George occasionally reflect an understanding between brothers that their mother was not to be worried unduly. On October 29, 1878, Albert wrote, "Burn this letter & do not tell mother its contents" at the top of a note in which he confided that "I have seen 18 men killed & shot since I left home & seen many others that ought to have been." (folder 261) The correspondence between Albert and his mother is represented here by his letters to her, which he sent frequently, as he was also sending her money. In the first years in the West, he often described opportunities he had to make money and promised that he would be able to support her more fully in the future. He was also very involved in family matters at home, and gave advice about handling the renovation of the house in Belvidere (Illinois), George's health, companionship for Sarah Ann, and financial matters.
George and Albert Wilbur also discussed business, specifically George's interest in the Pittsburgh Stamp Mill in Crested Butte, Colorado. There is considerable correspondence in 1896 when George wrestled with the mill's financial difficulties (folders 285-288). Albert drew on his experience as a stockholder in several mining companies, and on the easy access he had to Western miners and millers to offer George frequent advice about the mill. Another perspective on the matter can be found in George's letters from Colorado to his mother during the summers between 1890 and 1896 (folders 163-192) in addition to the letters to Ellen mentioned above.
After his marriage in 1891, Albert Wilbur relied on his wife Laura Bofinger Wilbur to write to his family, (folders 370-372, 477-487) and with the exception of his lengthy correspondence with George in 1896, Albert wrote less frequently than before. Laura's letters to George and her mother-in-law contain much domestic detail, including news of her daughter Helen, descriptions of her house and neighborhood, along with candid evaluations of Albert's economic instability.
Beginning in 1902 a large gap occurs in the correspondence between the brothers and their families. With the single exception of a 1907 letter from George to Albert detailing how he dispersed their mother's estate, there are no letters until 1923. The letters of 1923 do not, however, suggest that a long silence has been broken, and as the period of this gap correlates with a gap in George Wilbur's personal diaries, it may be that the brothers remained regular correspondents and that the correspondence and diaries have been separated from the rest of the collection. Albert wrote two letters to Ellen after George's death in 1931 expressing his sense of loss (folder 655c).
Other letters from the West can be found in George's Correspondence with Others, from his friends C. B. Loop, who traveled to California in 1874, (folder 384); M. C. Kasson, who traveled to Colorado via Dodge City, Kansas in 1875 (folder 386); and W. S. Thompson, who worked in the Quartermaster's office at Fort Leavenworth, Kansas 1871-1873 (folders 378-382).
The collection contains few letters to Albert Wilbur due to the fact he did not live with the Illinois branch of the family for very long. There is a folder of correspondence from others to Albert (folder 581), which contains a few letters written to him by his cousins while he visited Belvidere, Illinois. Also present in the folder is the invitation to his wedding.
George Wilbur's correspondence with his daughter, Susan Wilbur Jones (folders 341-369) contains letters she wrote to him as a young child. There is also a substantial run of letters she wrote from Wellesley. There are very few letters between Susan and her mother and aunt from this period. Susan describes her life at Wellesley, thanks him for presents, and comments on his news. It should also be noted that there is additional correspondence located in her Wellesley scrapbooks in series IV (folders 1776-1787). Carbon copies of George's letters to her appear in their later correspondence, which includes details about her three children while on vacation in Massachusetts.
Susan's correspondence with her mother and her aunt (nicknamed "Aunt Foo") were written while separated from them on trips, and contain miscellaneous descriptions of day to day life (folders 552-553). Susan's correspondence with her grandmother contains some of her earliest letters (folders 488-493), and some of the few letters written by Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur to someone other than George Wilbur in the collection. Susan's correspondence with Llewellyn Jones (folder 553a) includes letters from before their marriage. She also corresponded with her cousin E. P. Warren, an author and art collector who bought many pieces for the Museum of Fine Arts in Boston and recognized Susan's artistic nature (folder 553b), and "Mary," a companion to her parents in the 1920s (folder 553c-e). Susan's correspondence with others (folders 554-562) includes letters from Wellesley classmates after graduation and letters from other Warren cousins, including E. P. Warren's sister Cornelia Warren, a trustee of Wellesley. Later correspondence includes letters to, from, and about her children.
Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur's correspondence includes a set of correspondence about another unstable marriage within the family, that of Albert Gale and Carrie Cook, Sarah Ann's niece (folders 495-503). After Carrie left Albert for another man, Albert wrote Sarah Ann and, to a lesser extent, George Wilbur many letters full of creatively phrased denunciations of his ex-wife (folders 375-377). Carrie's letters are fewer in number, but they reveal her point of view of the marriage.
Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur's Correspondence with Others (folders 504-548) includes a letter from her husband George dated November 12, 1848, which is the only letter signed by him in the entire collection (folder 504). Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur was one of at least eight children, and lived far away from her siblings. The correspondence that her siblings and their children generated in exchanging news resulted in an extensive family correspondence. The letters are almost all incoming, and from family members, with a few scattered letters from friends. Included are letters from a young Helen Wilbur, Albert's daughter. Family charts have been appended to help identify family members.
George Wilbur's Correspondence with Others (folders 378-403) includes letters from friends at Champaign University, friends in Belvidere, postcards written in code (possibly masonic), and later letters written mostly by relatives, including a few carbon copies of George's letters to them. Ellen Rice Wilbur's Correspondence with Others (folders 568-577) is all incoming, and includes early letters from her mother, her sister Mary, her aunt Cornelia Warren, and friends from Rockford Female Seminary, as well as condolence letters after the death of her sister Susan and George.
Other Personal Correspondence (folders 586-597) consists of letters written to Susan C. Rice from her sisters, most written in 1861; Cook family members writing to other family members; letters possibly written to George Wilbur Senior; one letter written by Susan Wilbur Jones' husband Llewellyn Jones; and other letters written to unidentified recipients.
Series II, George W. Wilbur's Professional Papers document George Wilbur's legal career and is organized into twelve subseries, Cases: Contract Files, Cases: Long Term Individual Client Files, Cases: Mining Company Files, Cases: Probate Files, Cases: Real Estate Files, Cases: Street Improvements Files, Cases: Other Case Files, Cases: Fragments From Files, Professional Correspondence, Financial Records, Notebooks, and Printed Material. The series is housed in Boxes 28-77.
The Case files make up a large part of the collection, Boxes 28-66. Correspondence that was found filed with case records was left in the Case files, but readers should also consult the Professional Correspondence, as there is often correspondence relating to specific cases to be found there. Similar considerations apply to Bills and receipts, as some are to be found in the Case files, and the rest in the Financial Records. Much of the material in the Case files is fragile.
The Case files reflect the range of civil suits which made up the bulk of George Wilbur's practice. The Contract Files (folders 598-656) include suits over violations of contract for house decorating, plumbing, broken leases, failure to pay doctor's bills. Wilbur's Long Term Client Files contain the records of Michael and Robert L. Burke (folders 657-702). Michael Burke was a Chicago land owner that George defended in personal injury suits, who left his son $750,000 when he died in 1920. George Wilbur handled his estate and represented Robert Burke in a number of different cases. Burke was court-martialed for being absent without leave from the Army in 1918, sued by a woman for slander, had an auto accident in North Carolina, bought real estate in Florida, and sought treatment for chronic alcoholism.
Thomas Hulbert was another long term client of George Wilbur's (folders 703-730). Hulbert dealt in residential real estate in Chicago and Oak Park, Illinois and George Wilbur represented him from 1900-1930. Roswell Jones, a mortgage broker in Bellwood and Oak Park, Illinois, was George Wilbur's client from 1922-1930. Wilbur also defended his wife's aunt and uncle, Charlotte and Francis H. Rice, who were involved in a land dispute from 1886 to 1900 (folders 750-770).
There are two mining companies represented, the Pittsburgh Concentrating and Mining Company and the Ruby Chief Mining and Milling Company, both located outside of Crested Butte, Colorado. The Pittsburgh Company case (folders 771-782) involved a suit for improperly processing ore contracted to them. The Pittsburgh Company appealed and attempted to have the case moved to another county, then tried to get the case dismissed but could not because previous court fees had not been paid. Later correspondence revolves around the attorney's fees. There are also three printed pamphlets of appeals concerning the case. George Wilbur was not an attorney for the company, but was involved in the case as a stockholder and member of the Board of Directors. This is an anomaly in the Case files, for Wilbur served as attorney in every other case in the collection. The Ruby Chief Mining and Milling Company (folders 783-799) involved some of the same parties in a series of suits over stock. George Wilbur was both stockholder in and attorney for the company. The first folders in this section contain documents, correspondence, and receipts regarding the company that was collected as background information for the cases. Correspondence about these cases appears in Wilbur's Professional Correspondence in series II beginning in 1887.
There are twenty-one Probate cases (folders 800-881), in which Wilbur handled estates and filed suits on behalf of relatives challenging wills. His clients came from both Chicago and Oak Park, Illinois. The largest case file concerns the settlement of the estate of Agnes Weaver, described as a "distracted person," who owned property in Oklahoma and Michigan. The Real Estate cases (folders 882-945) concern the purchase of property, foreclosures, and the rights of property owners in Chicago, Oak Park, and Cicero, Illinois. There are a large number of Street Improvement cases (folders 946-1154), which concern the taxes associated with the cost of the improvements. The Street Improvements section is divided into Paving, Sewers, and Subway Cases in Chicago and Oak Park. The cases contain much information on Chicago and Oak Park city planning and residents. The Other Case Files (folders 1155-1255) contain records on assorted civil actions, including one, Gaskill vs. Forest Home (folder 1187), involving a suit brought by an African-American in 1913-1914 to bury his children in the same cemetery in which he had buried his wife, which, since her death, had become an all-white cemetery.
The Professional Correspondence files (folders 1264-1372) include correspondence pertaining to specific cases found in the Case files. The early correspondence, which dates from the time Wilbur first considered attending Union College of Law in Chicago, contains several letters of introduction to lawyers in Chicago. A Letterpress book (folder 1844) contains copies of his outgoing correspondence from the years 1879 to 1884. Correspondence prior to 1896 which is not in the Letterpress book is incoming. From 1896 forward the correspondence not in the Letterpress book switches to carbon copies of his outgoing letters only. Most of the letters from the 1890s and 1900s are about street improvement cases. There is a gap in the correspondence from 1907 to 1911, and then for the next eight years only a few letters from each year.
The Financial Records (folders 1373-1425), as mentioned above, should be used in conjunction with the Case files, as some of the Bills and receipts refer to specific cases represented in the Case files. The Notebooks (folders 1426-1433) include a pocket notebook which contains references to the Ruby Chief Mine's docket information and a few notes on the case in the back. The Notebooks also contain several case directories that George Wilbur devised to keep track of his cases.
Series III, George W. Wilbur's Personal and Business Papers, is organized into five subseries: Diaries, Personal Financial Records, Business Records, Writings, and Other Papers. The series is housed in boxes 78-94. The Diaries (folders 1442-1470) contain brief entries detailing both his personal life and his daily activities at the office. George Wilbur makes passing references to marketing the McLaughlin Smoke Consumer in the late 1880s, and writes during his trips to Colorado in the summers of 1890 and 1891. The diaries run from 1874 to 1895, skip 1896, and include one for 1897. There are no diaries from 1898 to 1925, but five volumes cover 1925, 1926, 1928, 1930, and 1931. The diaries in the 1920's and 1930's contain sporadic entries, which continue up to three weeks before his death.
Personal Financial Records contain a large and comprehensive run of Bills and Receipts kept by George Wilbur, his wife Ellen, and his sister-in-law Susan Rice, who lived with them (folders 1472-1536). The Bills and Receipts have been left in the order that they were found, seven roughly alphabetic runs over varying spans of years between 1872 and 1926. Large numbers of receipts from single merchants have been gathered into separate folders and placed in appropriate alphabetical order within each run of bills. Other materials in George's financial papers include a long run of Canceled Checks and Check Registers (folders 1537-1549). The thoroughness of the records, especially the Bills and Receipts, Canceled Checks, and Check Registers should provide an informative view of the spending habits of a middle class Chicago family at the turn of the century.
Also included in the Personal Financial Records is Housekeeping Correspondence (folders 1550-1559), with a file of correspondence from Irving Terwilliger, George's banker and good friend. Some of these letters contain personal content, but their principal focus is domestic finances so it was decided to keep them together here.
Business Records include records for the McLaughlin Smoke Consumer Company (folders 1569-1573), of which Wilbur owned part beginning in 1884. He marketed the Smoke Consumer, with only moderate success, until 1896. Included in this subseries are Bills and receipts, Contracts, and Correspondence with those who purchased the device.
Also in Business Records are the records for Wilbur's activities as stockholder in Ruby Chief Mining and Milling Company and Pittsburgh Concentrating and Mining Company, as well as his purchase of the Pittsburgh Mill (folders 1574-1625). Included here are Bills and receipts, Canceled checks, Contracts and deeds, Correspondence, Diaries and expense books, Maps, and Printed material. This subseries contains material pertaining to Wilbur's business interests in mining and milling. Many closely related items concerning his legal services to mining companies are located in series II in the Professional Correspondence, and Bills and Receipts section of the Financial Records subseries, and in the subseries Cases: Mining Company Files.
Series IV, Other Family Papers, is organized into seven subseries: Cook and Rice Family Papers, Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur, Ellen Rice Wilbur, Albert H. Wilbur, Susan W. Rice, Susan Wilbur Jones, and Unidentified. The series is housed in boxes 95-107.
The Cook and Rice Family Papers consists of a small section of Cook family material and a larger section of Rice family material. The Cook Family Documents (folders 1638-1640) contain material from 1737, the earliest in the collection. The Rice Family materials focuses on Francis H. Rice, Ellen's uncle, and George H. Rice, her father (folders 1643-1674). These two men were partners who bought and sold merchandise, mostly shoes, boots, hats, and gloves which they sold in a store in Belvidere, Illinois. An account book (folder 1645) indicates that they sold goods to a man named M. M. Walker and that Francis H. Rice later became involved in the ownership of that store. Present in the collection are their Correspondence, Financial Papers, and Documents. There are many papers involving the transactions with the shoemakers Whipple, Alley & Billings of Chicago. This section also includes research notes on Stephen Flagg, who served in a Massachusetts regiment in the American Revolution (folder 1642).
The family papers for each individual include Account books, Bills and Receipts, Canceled Checks, Business Correspondence, Writings, Printed Material, Notebooks, and Realia. Ellen Rice Wilbur's papers (folders 1687-1723) contain correspondence about her property in Oak Park and Belvidere, principally concerning the rental of the property in Belvidere and later the proposition to sell it to the town as a site for the Carnegie Library. Other correspondence includes mail from S. D. Warren & Company, which sent her stock dividends, three letters spanning 1907-1909 regarding arrangements to board her daughter Susan with Katharine Lee Bates at Wellesley (folder 1709), and three folders regarding her involvement in the 1916 Rockford College reunion (folders 1711-1713). The printed material includes a Rockford Alumna from January 1932 which carries a brief obituary (folder 1859). A small collection of similar letters from S. D. Warren & Company, bills and receipts and writings, belonging to Susan W. Rice follow Ellen Wilbur's papers.
Susan Wilbur Jones' papers include a long run of Canceled checks which illuminate her daily expenses (folders 1741-1758), and seven folders of juvenilia (folders 1764-1770). A brief notice from the society page describes a party she attended as a child at Mrs. Frank Lloyd Wright's house in Oak Park (folder 1771). There are also a few items that probably belonged to her husband, Llewellyn Jones. There are several sources of Wellesley College material in her papers. Most memorabilia is found in two Scrapbooks (folders 1776-1787), while the printed material includes programs and handbooks and a short run of the College News (folders 1861-1866).
A final subseries of Unidentified Items (folders 1788-1792) contain materials written in an unknown hand or for which the correlation to the Wilbur, Cook, or Rice families has not been determined. They include a curious "Account book," containing entries at three or four day intervals in 1883-85 under predominantly women's names, most of whom resided in Belvidere (folder 1788).
Series V, Printed Material, is organized into three subseries, Church Publications, Newspapers, and Miscellaneous. The Newspapers subseries includes issues of the Belvidere Standard, for which George wrote unsigned articles on Belvidere happenings, with his pencilled signature at the end of the articles indicating his authorship (folders 1871-1877).
Series VI, Photographs, is organized into three subseries, Identified People, Unidentified People by Place, and Other Photographs, and is housed in boxes 109-110. The photographs are mostly cabinet cards and cartes de visite with a few cyanotypes and tintypes represented. Photographs of unidentified people have been organized by place of photographer, as they represent the specific parts of the country in which George's family and friends lived. The names of Western photographers represented here (from California and Kansas) have been noted. The Other Photographs include Cyanotypes of the St. Louis Sampling & Testing Works, as well as another factory, and probably have something to do with George's mining interests (folders 1834-1835).
The Restricted Fragile Papers in Boxes 114-119 consist of originals for which preservation photocopies have been made.
OUTLINE OF THE COLLECTION
Series I. Personal Correspondence
WILBUR, GEORGE W.
--Correspondence with Sarah Ann Cook Wilbur
--Correspondence with Albert H. Wilbur
--Correspondence with Ellen Rice Wilbur
--Correspondence with Susan Wilbur Jones
--Correspondence with Laura Bofinger Wilbur
--Correspondence with Susan W. Rice
--Correspondence with Albert and Carrie Cook Gale
--Correspondence with Others
--Invitations and Christmas Cards
WILBUR, SARAH ANN COOK
--Correspondence with Albert H. Wilbur
--Correspondence with Ellen Rice Wilbur
--Correspondence with Laura Bofinger Wilbur
--Correspondence with Susan Wilbur Jones
--Correspondence with Susan W. Rice
--Correspondence with Albert and Carrie Cook Gale
--Correspondence with Others
--Invitations
JONES, SUSAN WILBUR
--Correspondence with Ellen Rice Wilbur